so a lot of the work in non equilibrium statmech
looks at the trajectories and the process of like
locally reversing entropy
sorting air particles
and putting you fast moving air particles on the right
and slow moving air particles on the left
that was
that was maybe useful for thinking that you could
you could pump entropy out of the system
hi, I'm Slater Stich with Bain Capital Ventures
and today we're talking with Jascha Sohl-Dickstein
Jascha is best known for inventing diffusion models
and
that's the technology behind many of today's creative
AI applications
so if you've used a text to image generation model
for example, something like Midjourney Ideogram
DALL-E, Stable Diffusion, Black Forest Labs
Imagen from Google
all of those products are based on diffusion models
in today's interview
we will talk about the original diffusion paper from
2015. we'll talk about
Jascha's interpretation of all of the diffusion
research that came after that
and we'll also get into the theoretical physics
that inspired diffusion
in the first place
and led to many of the key insights
in that original paper
enjoy
in 2015, you wrote this paper
I think it was deep
unsupervised learning
using Nonequilibrium Thermodynamics
maybe to start
could you talk a little bit about what the research
world and deep learning looked like
at that phase
this was pretty early
I think that this was a couple of years after AlexNet
we'd just gotten to the point of being at you
know sort of human level performance for image
classification, like little one
yeah, you know, anything generative
so this is really early to work on generative problems
in a way
and what made you interested in this problem then
sort of what was the prehistory of this paper
yeah, this was
so maybe the the
the prehistory of this paper is that I had done a
PhD in Computational Neuroscience
and a question that we thought a lot about
was how the brain
learned the representations that that it learned
and there's one class of hypotheses in neuroscience
for for how that learning happens
which is that maybe the brain
is building a like probabilistic model
of its input. and what that means
is
maybe the brain is solving a task where
it sees an image
and it tries as hard as it can
to accurately assign like
how probable would this image be to occur in the world
and if the brain does a really
really, really good job of this, then in some sense
it like understands everything that's possible
to know about the world
like, yeah, you can describe the full distribution
over things that you see in the world
then you must like somehow have Learned
everything about
about what makes something likely in the world
unlikely in the world
yeah
sorry, I'll go for those
I was gonna say that that in a way is like a very, I
don't know, like
like abstract or sort of like a high minded aspiration
and so he sort of had almost this like
world model idea of, yeah
I've wanted to learn world models
yeah. and
I spent a lot of my PhD trying to learn world models
and then looking to see if
the same representations that were learned
inside the world models
were also found in like recordings from from the brain
yeah. and
the answer to that is, well, it was
was often hard to know
but often, often you could find
you could find a place where the answer was yes
yeah. and maybe maybe in parallel to that
I had like this
this I'd been a physics undergrad
and I was doing biophysics PhD
and we had this like group of people at Berkeley
where I did my PhD
who were really interested in non equilibrium
physical kinetics
yeah, and
non equilibrium
so okay, equilibrium to school mechanics is
you like have a system
and the system has no inputs and no outputs
and you let it sit there for a really
really, really long time
and it like settles
to whatever kind of ground state is going to be in
yeah
so maybe you put a whole bunch of particles in a box
and you look at the distribution
of where the particles are going to be in that box
and maybe all the particles
start off on one side of the box
but you like let the system settle
the particles like flow back and forth
like the gas fills the box
and and you get some like equilibrium distribution
non equilibrium system mechanics
is when you you model systems that haven't settled yet
yeah. and maybe they haven't settled yet
because they're constantly getting new inputs
and outputs
or maybe they haven't settled yet because you're
like seeing them early in time instead of really
really late in time
yeah, and it's kind of like
there was there's at least no in correspondences
between
equilibrium statistical mechanics
and a lot of concepts in machine learning
there's like a class of like
models of machine learning called energy based models
and these in fact map directly onto like
energy based probabilistic models in in statmech
and, and even more than that
like you can map any kind of
probabilistic model into energy based model
yeah, so we know kind of how to build a connection
between equilibrium thermodynamic mechanics and
machine learning
we do not
did not historically know how to build a connection
between like non
equilibrium systems of mechanics and machine learning
and so, and so I can kind of the
the
motivating question was
I kind of had these like
thoughts in my head of like all this nanotechnology
stuff is really cool
and it seems like
there's these missing connections to machine learning
and I'm really interested in representation learning
and and
kind of combined them and somehow ended up
like writing the first diffusion models. paper. yeah
one thing that I wanted to ask about specifically is
you know, so in that paper
you mentioned two other papers as inspiration
so one of them is this paper by (Christopher) Jarzynski
and I think there's other paper by Radford M. Neal
yeah, and so Jarzynski is a businessman
you know, Neal is a statistician
and both of these papers
don't seem like they're about something in image
generation, you know
they're about
sort of transforming one distribution into another
yeah
especially when one of those distributions is kind of
you know, intractable or sort of devil to compute
so how did you look at that and say like
this is probably gonna be pretty good
for image generation
like where did that idea come from
so maybe
let me just talk about those papers for a moment
yes
because those are those are those papers are awesome
and maybe there's two ways in which those papers like
were really kind of exciting. maybe maybe
one of them is
there are these like laws of thermodynamics
and there's this like second law of thermodynamics
and the second law of thermodynamics is an inequality
it says that it
says that that free energy is always going to
to decrease or that entropy is always going to
to increase
whereas there's this like
paper by groszinsky was in I want to say like 94
it was like, yes, this might be yeah, yeah, maybe 97
it's quite old, but it was like
it's interesting
because that paper shows that
you can rewrite the second law of
thermodynamics
as an Equality rather than an inequality
yeah, you can rewrite it as
the, so 2nd law of thermodynamics says that
the change in
free energy is always less than the work you put in
the, this, this paper shows that you can write this as
E to the, the
E to the change in the free energy
is equal to the expectation of E to the work you put in
so it's, it's amazing because this
like foundational relationship in
in physics
was like written with an inequality
when it could have been written with inequality
for like many, many, many decades
and the math that is used
is actually quite simple, like
like
you know, high school or early college level level math
so this is like
super low hanging fruit that just no one noticed
and that's always kind of exciting because, yeah, like
maybe there's more of this
the
the Radford Neal's paper is kind of interesting because
it discovered the same relationship
but framed in a totally different way
like Jerzinsky had
like written down this relationship in terms of like
work and energy and like physical quantities
and they even used some like in the original paper
some like super physicsy
um, um, like Liouville's theorem style, like
like math and like constraints and whatnot
whereas like Radford Neal was like
proving something about machine learning
he was like, showing that, um, here is a way that you can
estimate normalizing constants
by sampling trajectories
between two different distributions
yeah. and it turned out that that like
his work mapped exactly onto the physics work
it also his paper came out just a few years later
it would have been like
utterly in some way satisfying
if we live in the alternate universe where
where the machine learning result was first and like
prove something basic about physics
you could actually kind of almost read the point in
in Radford Neal's paper
where he realizes that
it was already noticed in physics
but, but so those are both very cool papers
and they're also very exciting
because they're like discovering
fundamental new relationships, like
really quite late that should be unfound
long time before
in terms of
why I thought that this would work for images, yeah
I mean, I had some like
intuitions, but I think
I also have to admit that
it worked far better than I probably guessed
it would when I started playing with it
I think kind of the intuition is
the way in which diffusion models work
is
you start with your data distribution
you start with like clean images
and you slowly corrupt that image with noise
you
you slowly
allow that image to undergo a diffusion process and
and look more and more like either a
draw from a Gaussian or a draw from like a horrendous
well, yeah, on
and then rather than trying to map from
noise back to an image
in one go
you instead get to break it apart into lots of very
very small pieces
so like your generative process is like
let's start with the noisiest case and very
very, very slowly
predict the image that had a little bit less noise
and a little bit less noise
a little bit less noise
and I think it's this like
ability to take many, many, many steps that that
makes the problem a lot easier
yeah, I mean
so from the outside
the thing that seems sort of surprising to me is like
so like on a very small time scale
I sort of believe that you could sort of
reverse the diffusion problem
like it sort of looks roughly the same
forwards as it does backwards on like
really small time scale
but like, you know
the thing that's surprising is that
you can go all the way back
in these like
solid iterative steps
like, you know, the
glass breaks and you can sort of run time backwards
so like put the glass together and like
that's the thing that seems super surprising to me
yes. yeah
did you did you look at these papers and say like
well, this is the thing that we could use to like
recover the true data distribution
like this is this is sort of like the right
tool to use for that problem
or is it kind of surprising
I, I
think I thought it should work from the start
but I'm
always unreasonably optimistic about my own ideas
and my own projects
yeah. and 90% of them don't work at all
so, so you should like, like
calibrate that however you like
yeah
I definitely had a lot of conversations
especially early on the project where
where, where people were like
slightly aghast that had a
like, like in the same way you can unmix pudding
yeah. yeah. yeah
yeah. it does seem quite surprising
but it sounds like it wasn't surprising
yeah, I mean, I think it's, it's
it's
maybe the key is that
you're training a model to do this, right
you're not just like
running the sequence and hoping it happens to like
go back to where it started
you're like training a model to like
decrease the entropy and like
like push it towards, towards a known distribution. yeah
we're, I feel like there were these
like early
there were some niceties about getting diffusion
models to work
that are sort of a little surprising
so like, you know, you remove a lot of data
you know, by default
if you sort of like try to predict an image
that sort of would have generated that data
you necessarily have like
a more diffuse distribution than like
the single point that you started with
so that's why you get these sort of like fuzzy images
and you try to go backwards
and I kind of imagine those problems as seeming like
intractable things
but it seems like it worked quite well
you know, even in this initial paper
yeah, yeah, it worked. it worked certainly for the for the
for the year which was published
it worked, it worked quite well. yeah
were you surprised when you saw those initial like
seafar images that you generated
you know, when
when you read those thermodynamic mechanics papers
and you sort of saw this general machinery
yeah
I still think it's like quite a leap to go from like
okay, we're gonna go from that to like image generation
because I sort of have in my head like
yeah, we have these sort of particle models
and, you know, it sort of makes sense that
maybe we should be able to sort of
transform between these two distributions
but
many people wouldn't have made the leap to saying like
this is going to be really good for generating like
samples from the data distribution
yeah, you know, so like intuition for why that
happened or why that was true are really interesting
maybe, I mean
so a lot of the work in non equilibrium stat mech
looks at
the trajectories and the process of like locally
reversing entropy
yeah
so, so maybe maybe from some point of view, it wasn't
like they weren't thinking about images
but they were thinking about like Maxwell's demons
like
sorting air particles and putting the fast moving air
particles on the right and the
slow moving air particles on the left
so you have a hot side and a cold side
or
they were thinking about kind of these processes that
could
exchange information for entropy
so Maxwell demon me an example of this, right where
where
the sorting process itself requires like
information processing and storage in it
and like that has a has a cost that compensates for the
you know
benefit that you get of like sorting the particles
but there was a lot of this kind of like
idea of there being like
crossover between like
ideas and information and ideas in thermodynamics
and so maybe that was
that was maybe useful for thinking that you could
you could pump entropy out of the system
yeah, you could recover this
like very complicated distribution
yeah. well, one thing I want to ask about is
so like around this time
and this is as a sort of outside perspective
the way that it seems is that I think
Gans came out sort of right before
this first diffusion barrier
and then but they were also it was still very early
they didn't work that well
and then I think
Alec Grafford had the DC Gan paper
that came out a little bit after
it was a bit later
yeah. and then there was this era where, you know
it seems from the outside that like
for the next five years
most of the emphasis in Abbot generation was in Gan
so we kind of went through this
mini ice age for diffusion models
is that true? was there interesting research
that was happening in diffusion
that was sort of less well appreciated
or just less advanced
it was it was mostly mostly forgotten
yeah
and there's probably okay, so there probably like GANs
which which
which were the
the one that everyone is most excited about
or yeah, at least enjoyed working the most
there were very small new hers
and there were also like flow based models
and those all came out
and then there were diffusion models
and those all came out in a very, very short time
relative to each other
I think they probably
I suspect that
I know this is true for like
the diffusion models and my GANs and the AES
but I suspect for you there's also that
probably everyone was like
developing ideas in parallel
and the whole
occasion times just
didn't quite line up
the
diffusion models had a small number of follow up papers
and then
ended up like kind of I think mostly being forgotten
I including I should say I probably
I moved on to work on other things
that I also thought were exciting
and yeah, and and you know, probably
in a different world
I like pushed on that for another few papers
and maybe yeah
but I think they also weren't
diffusion models
have some advantages over other techniques
they
might have an advantage image quality that's debatable
but they have an advantage
in that they're very, very guideable
yes. so you control very, very well
what they generate
and they also are like very nicely
like it's kind of the same thing
but they're like invisible
like if you want to do in painting or you want to
combine them with a classifier or
you want to control them some other ways
they work very well for that
they are more expensive
so I think at the time, like
we were like pushing the compute limits
we had to like generate
ugly CIFAR images
yeah. and like, I think
saying that people should spend 1,000 x to compute
to like generate CIFAR images was not a
it wasn't like a winning. yeah
and that was because of the number of reverse steps
as you see that
because you have to like
run many reverse steps in order to do it
did you
during this era where sort of view is like the GAN
VAE era
did you have the intuition at the time that like, okay
you know
in the long run, it's going to be diffusion models
because like
I think that's sort of where it's come around to today
and sort of most of the best commercial
you know
image generation and generates out through that
at least it seems to me that like for maybe
2021 until now
everything has been diffusion
yes. during that like six year period
did you have the intuition of like, well
obviously diffusion models are right
and all this like again
and yeah, you style is not
no, I still don't have that intuition actually. I, I
there are many different things
which determine model quality
there's like quality of the training data
there's quantity, the training data
there's like the
architecture that you're using to build the model
so like what what machine
how you're wiring the neurons together, essentially
and then there's a framework like
objective function
and like training process
like GAN or diffusion or whatever
and then there's like things like the optimizer
and I think that
there are many tasks currently
I think most image video
audio tasks
where the diffusion models seem to be the best choice
right now. yeah
but the gap is not that huge
yeah, like you
could train an auto regressive model to do
any of those tasks
and you could train it as well
and it would probably cost you more compute
and it would be like
you'd have to do more awkward things
in order to guide the generation
but yeah, but
all of these model classes are capable of
up doing the same task
it's just like kind of trade off at the margin
maybe. yeah
makes sense. maybe, you know
one other paper
I want to ask you about is to the DDPM paper
yes. so yeah, yeah
what was your reaction when that came out
like, what did you think when you
I added a super cool sign like drop
then Ho shared a draft with me and I, I was excited
I was like, oh, you found that paper. that's great
that
built on it. I'm super happy he wrote that paper
and it was very gracious of him to like give
give credit back to the the original diffusion word to
I, I think when I read the paper, I did
I still did not realize how transformative it would be
I think I had
have had this picture in my head that like
there are lots of generic bottling approaches
and if you push on any of them
you can get them into roughly the same bar
ballparker quality
yeah. and so I was like, oh
diffusion models are in the same class
as everything else
yeah, I didn't
I didn't expect them to take off to the way they have
acted mostly for their
like non, non purely loss based advantages
yeah
I should also say
in parallel, the Yang Song at Stanford was
after the same time as Jonathan
I was writing this paper
he was pursuing like score based
yeah
he's like score based approaches where he was like
doing Langevin Sampling
while annealing, annealing the temperature
which looks a lot
I think it was like experiencing conversion
evolution towards
towards like the diffusion based
generative models
and I don't think
he wasn't initially aware of the diffusion stuff
so I think, I think probably like
like Jonathon Ho published this paper
I think
the Song would have gotten very similar results in
like a year or two
probably means there were like
three other labs that were also like
working on it. but yeah
yeah, that's my maybe the last thing I'd love to
give your thoughts on is like
so, you know
Sander has this blog post that's like
here's 20 different interpretations of what's going on
in diffusion models
and, you know
you can sort of pick each of those papers out of it
like, you know
sort of here's the DDPM interpretation I've had
and sort of here's some ways of looking at
the sort of the original score based
playing out dynamics thing
here's how like the flow based Mad Yang give you
this is all like
these are riffs on the same idea
and it's sort of a convergent evolution story
do you think that some of these ideas are sort of
you know, meaningfully different? and we sort of
you know
if we pushed further in that tech tree direction
we could get to a different place
maybe both
yeah, I think it's like the fact that we can
tell the story of this model class
from so many starting points
I think is very suggestive that there's like
it's like somehow like a convergence evolution, like
yeah, that we were gonna get to
I, I do think different
perspectives are
likely
to
provide different capabilities and trade offs
if you use the like kind of propeller graphical model
perspective on it
then that like suggests
some accelerated sampling techniques
which you probably wouldn't get to otherwise
which are really, really nice
similarly, consistency models. yeah
yeah. and the consistency models are, are, are
are again, Yang Song be amazing
but, but, but are
are another like, like
kind of
thinking about it from the flow based perspective
yeah, like you wouldn't
you wouldn't get to those
if you weren't thinking about kind of the flow based
version of it
yeah
I think, I think there's
there's always it's always useful
they'll think about a problem from
from multiple perspectives
yes. I guess
like another thing I'd be curious about is like
this probably seems like a unusual
maybe somewhat weird research area in Cirque 2015
there's probably things like that now
I sort of thunk at, you know, if
you had infinite time to sort of like
pull ideas like this from physics
specifically for maybe image or video generation
sort of in the neighborhood of diffusion models
yeah. are there things that you think are, you know
equally weird, but maybe underdeveloped
like I sort of feel because you wrote this landmark PR
you know, the tech tree, there's like a big trunk
yeah
you know, that goes like in the direction of that paper
yeah. but maybe you would have written, you know
three different papers if you had
sort of got pulled in different directions
it would have led us on to different development paths
yeah, I think
I think the diffusion models have like grown to a thicket
like I can't even read every paper like it
I think people are exploring
a neighboring space quite densely
I do though think that like
if I was going to work on something
that I hope would be impactful
today, and I was gonna make it weird
yeah, I wouldn't be in the space of modeling images
yeah, but
there are I can riff on this tiny bit and
and but the ideas I have are like
like someone who's like a grad student now
is gonna have like
much fresher, better ideas
yeah, but like, okay, so a few examples
maybe one of them is
we built this like deep tech tree on top of like
turing machines
yeah, but now, but we're using most of that compute for
is like non-turing computation
like we need systems that take inputs
and then produce outputs
in a non linear fashion from those inputs
and with some kind of like
statistical properties of the input output mapping
you should probably like
look at some of the like infinite width literature
if you want to like
characterize what
maybe those statistical properties should be
but there's like some like
statistical properties
we believe are important for the input output mapping
and it needs to be non linear
and it needs to have a lot of knobs
you can turn to change the mapping
yeah, it doesn't need to like
run if else statements or for looped or anything
it just needs to be a complicated
non linear adjustable system
and I
think that we're implementing these systems using
like logic gates
because we have this deep tech tree
but you could imagine like a
taking a very non turing kind of approach
and
that could be that could be super fun and super cool
there's yeah
well, that was like a sort of analog computing idea
or what do you mean by sort of non lunch
yeah
yeah, I mean, there's a few ways you could do it. right
so, so analog computing would be would be one like
I mean, one version of this is you find like
a physical substrate
that that you can just directly use
another way to do it would be to
we a lot of the complexity around our current training
has to do with implementing back prop
and if you could find a way to train your model
based only on on forward props, then that might
hmm
yeah, like allow you to throw away just a lot of the
supporting complexity and hardware and by time. and yeah
there's like maybe another one is
okay, so machine learning has this like character that
it's an idea that people had tried
in the like 60s and the 80s
and maybe especially in the 80s
they tried
architectures very similar to what we're doing today
and it didn't work
and the reason it didn't work is because
it was a good idea
but we didn't have enough compute
and we didn't have enough data
yeah, you
can maybe think about
what other ideas have that same character
and and one one example, I think actually Andrej Karpathy
Karpathy suggested this
but I think one example is like evolutionary computing
yeah, so in evolutionary computing
we know it works. we know evolution works over yet
but when people have
tried to do evolutionary computing
it's mostly failed historically
and
a very likely reason that is mostly scaled
failed is that
is that it just hasn't had
the scale of like compute or training data necessary
to make it work. yeah
yeah. so it's sort of like all of these
all this work that was done on it
like 30 years ago or something like that
you know, the fact that it looks like a dead tree
is mostly because like
it was so start for compute
yeah. and in fact, maybe we should be tried again now
yeah, maybe, maybe, maybe go back to that and make it work
meta-learning has that same character maybe
where where we know that given
enough compute and enough data
learned
functions always outperform hand designed functions
but we still hand designer optimizers
and hand designer loss functions
and hand designer architectures
and there's like some work in meta-learning, but I
I think it hasn't nearly lived up to the like
I think there's a lot of room for a webinar papers
yeah, they're super interesting
well
maybe, maybe just one closing gush now to ask you is
so you, you write this
you know, very famous paper
in 2015
and sort of creates like the modern diffusion paradigm
I think maybe some of the things that happened
subsequent to that
were not surprising to
I'll sort of regard them as things that
you know, there's not a big belief update for them
yeah, but probably some things were quite surprising
that are the next
you know, 10 years
I'm curious as you look back
what was most surprising to you
where you think of like
I would not have predicted this when I read this paper
and oh man. yeah, I, I, um
in 2015
we were modeling 32 by 32 image patches poorly. yeah
I would
not have predicted then
that in less than 10 years, we would be generating like
video and audio
that was nearly indistinguishable from, from reality
yeah, I think just the raw
capabilities of these models has been
has been utterly surprising to me. amazing
awesome. well, thanks so much for doing this
really enjoyed our conversation
it was a pleasure. thanks, Aria